[Music]
welcome to another episode of head first
with dr. hill today's guest is Daniel
schmuck Tim burger who is a co-founder
and R&D director of the neuro hacker
collective which sounds kind of exciting
so Dan is going to tell us all kinds of
cool things today and dig into his
history a little bit and some of the
projects he's working on so welcome to
the show today Daniel thanks for having
me it's good to be here with you yeah
happy to have you so first of all what
is this collective of neuro hackers you
are assembling it sounds like a you know
sort of pie-in-the-sky big project where
you're hit you're aiming for a lot of
world-changing goals but can you unpack
a little bit for us what your your
approach here yeah so by neuro hacking
we mean anything that can optimize the
mind brain interface and the function
thereof so this is cognitive and
psychomotor and health and well-being
and so we could roughly define it as
well-being optimization but even larger
than that we think of it as sovereignty
optimization people's capacity to make
good choices right to be adaptive which
is a function of intelligence of agency
of sentient soul together and there's
obviously a kind of human software right
psychology here and there's human
Hardware physiology involved and we know
that's a software hardware divide in
humans is a plastic one it's
continuously inter affecting each other
and so you know your work with
neurofeedback is neuro hacking the other
people you've had on the show to
discussing meditation etc is all in that
space so we're interested in all
categories of technologies that can
meaningfully increase the homeostatic
capacity the dynamics as you like to
call them yeah of the human neuro
regulatory system and thereby increase
people's capacity for complex thinking
emotional resilience etc and the reason
why collective is anyone that is doing
meaningful work here we want to figure
out how we can participate at a research
level and at a you know information
product level etc so like us
walking here together is is awesome
shape koshering information in the space
that's great so you say sovereignty it's
an interesting way to way to frame that
agency what do you mean by I mean what
what kinds of things are bottlenecks to
human agency that appear to be a mere
affected by things we can do to the
brain like what how can we affect agency
in tractable ways what are you saying
what are you exploring yeah so by agency
here we mean the the actuator capacity
of a complex system the ability to act
on and in the world okay send chance is
kind of roughly related to our scent our
sensory input capacity intelligence to
our information processing of that
sensory input so that those exist in a
closed-loop take in information about
the world which is internal and external
sensing process it to inform choice make
choice get that about that choice
recursively upregulate and so on the
agency side on the capacity to act
obviously that requires the capacity to
have good information and information
processing so there's good choice in
forming it right it also requires
impulse control yeah yeah one can
actually have executive function and all
that they now come to bear it also
requires the it on the you know kind of
choice making side of it requires the
capacity to think through things using
different frameworks right critical
thinking frameworks systemic thinking
frameworks lateral thinking etc but also
in the agency side emotional resilience
is a key factor so that as one is
working with things and difficulties
come they can process that
physiologically and psychologically in
ways that empower them to continue to
learn rather than get shut down and so
when we look at the physiology of that
we know a lot about how dopamine about
how adrenal hormones about how you know
many different aspects of neural
chemistry and physiology are involved in
one sense of drive one sense of reward
dynamics that can predispose
dysfunctional or more functional
patterns of human behavior increased
sense of capacity psychologically
physiologically etc
so again we're back to this somewhat
soft division between the software and
the hardware so on the hardware side
things as you said like impulsivity or
executive function
I think you'e Bleakley referred to
working memory essentially which is from
my perspective the biggest bottleneck in
human performance and one that appears
to be the least responsive to change but
also ways of thinking about emotional
regulation and decision-making criteria
I'm much more familiar with the
physiology side you know the biohacking
idea is on the brain not the mind
largely what are you seeing of some
interesting ways that we can get into
cognitive change so the core
psychological brain mind question right
is at the core of the philosophy of
neuroscience the philosophy of line the
philosophy of science itself right
because the brain mind gets into the
brain physics and the question of what
is consciousness what is physics how do
they interact is there bi-directional
causation beyond the scope of what we're
probably going to dive into here but
it's definitely at the core of what's
informing the whatever you do okay so
how in any model of philosophy of mind
however we address this it's clear that
what's happening physiologically is
affecting one subjective experience and
what's happening one subjective
experience is being mirrored on you know
affecting the physiology side and so we
can obviously modify brain chemistry the
whole field of Psychiatry is focused on
this right second row pharmacology and
not just pharmacology but neuro tech in
general sure sure to affect cognitive
and psychological predispositions and
capacities we can also do practices that
are involving one's direction of their
own attention and subjective experience
whether we're talking about cognitive
behavioral therapy CBT DBT other
psychotherapeutic processes or even what
we call more kind of mindfulness
processes of proprioception pay
attention to various sensations in the
body parts of the body and what's the
changes as I'm sure you've done a lot of
on
physiology EEG processes and then what's
the capacity for neuroplastic changes in
the connectome with enough time and
input in there so it's not only that the
division between hardware and software
is soft it's they are both Co evolving
all the time and interdependent and
changing each others you alluded to yeah
yeah I mean I have to say I'm a I'm a
reductionist in this space a little bit
so for me the mind is simply the part of
the brain that we are aware of and
experiencing and and I kind of don't go
below that I have a somewhat of a
Buddhist perspective where I don't
really believe in consciousness
I believe in moments of consciousness
but not the overarching I like if the
brain falls over from my perspective
that's it there's there's there is no
mind outside of the the coupe Oriole
boundary of the skull so to speak even
though I know that there are non-local
phenomenon that we're observing now in
the brain and I'm sure you are deeper
into this idea of begin the physics
affecting consciousness I've just saw a
saw paper last week that showed that
water has some strange kind of non-local
I hate to use word but quantum tunneling
in microtubules apparently under some
conditions it appears like water
molecules have a superposition and can
be in more than one place at once inside
of cells this is getting very quickly
out of the realm of anything we fully
understand but do you think that we are
getting to a place where we're starting
to run up against the you know the edge
of wander said science and we're off in
the quantum you know weeds or is there
something here that we're making actual
progress in you know actionable
understanding of the brain both so
quantum mechanics brings us to the limit
of understand ability not just what we
currently understand that the upper
limits on epistemology have
measurability them yeah and even beyond
measurability the upper limits on
ontology Reitman
Heisenberg's theorem doesn't just say we
can't know what it is because of
measurement issues it says it's and it
depends on which interpretation of
quantum mechanics but standard model
interpretation its fundamental nature is
not yet defined independent of an
observation dynamic that observation the
subject object interaction Arco defining
at the level of quantum particles mhm
it's a very philosophically weird thing
for us to think about using the
intuition that we have from traditional
larger particle physics yeah now we have
historically kind of written that off as
just super weird phenomena that happens
only below atoms then cancels itself out
at the level of atoms and so we don't
have to worry about it the topic of
quantum amplification are there quantum
phenomena that then affect the behavior
of things at a mesoscopic level at a
Newtonian physics level or right uh-huh
so this is you know the work of Stewart
Kaufman the work of other people at
Santa Fe Institute of complexity science
the work of people like Stuart Hameroff
have really shown quite clearly the
quantum amplification does happen which
means that the non-deterministic right a
causal phenomena at a quantum level are
affecting macroscopic behavior at the
level of brains that still follows
probability distributions but not
determinism and I so this is this is a
very interesting very important weird
topic and the whole topic of
microtubules microtubules in neurons and
specific and superposition dynamics and
quantum information processing is one of
the like kind of interesting cutting
edges in the field the work of Stuart
Hameroff and Roger Penrose kind of open
that space up and the work of dr. honor
bond there's a few people kind of
working in that space and it is only
scratching at the surface of what we can
claim to know well but there's already
application happening and things like
transcranial ultrasound that were based
on the philosophy from there that seemed
to be having positive result so it's a
super interesting field interesting
that's oh it's wonderful thanks for
unpacking that just a touch for us I
would say one more thing about that yeah
the Buddhist perspective the kind of
John Cyril idea of that the mind is what
the brain does
[Music]
this is one interpretation of Buddhism
right there different schools as yours
I'm sure have very different
interpretations here obviously the
foundational idea of what's real
in Buddhism coming from Vedanta was that
consciousness is what we actually have a
stronger sense of no ability on than
physics mm-hmm right sure sure and so
their model was well I know that I'm
experiencing something there's an
experiencer here I don't know that what
I'm experiencing is what I think it is
but in an almost kind of Descartes like
way there is some witness that is
witnessing changing phenomena that is
prima facie real right so their model is
be was reductionist in the opposite
direction either that that consciousness
is an emergent property of physics which
is where physicalism science has gone
they saw the rest of universe as either
not real or an emergent property of
consciousness and that that kind of
idealism physicalism divide is right at
the heart of what we're figuring out
when we're studying consciousness via
objective methods in brain science but
correct if i'm wrong but you know old
school you know early pali buddhists
wouldn't consider consciousness a
phenomena outside of momentary
experience i mean i nietzsche
impermanence the nature of reality is
transient
so even consciousness the I always even
fall back to the metaphor classic
metaphor ship of theseus you know a
thought experiment here's a model ship
if I replace one plank is it the same
ship
how about two how about three at what
point is this capital I self the same if
every seven or eight years all the
molecules my body are completely
different and have been replaced you
know this is where it fundamentally
breaks down for me personally in terms
of consciousness but would the you know
the Vedanta approach say that there is a
cohesive sense of consciousness or is it
emergent property of just you know
having a meatsuit so Sanskrit has a lot
more words
that have a lot more specificity in
their definition than just consciousness
and self-awareness and they're actually
very key distinctions in their
philosophic system okay and again there
are different interpretations and in
these systems but the Buddhists
traditionally say that the foundation of
reality is neither self nor non-self
because that distinction doesn't exist
at that level that the rational
distinction of the concept of self other
than self is more superficial than the
foundation of reality right it's its
ontological a less primary okay so the
idea that it's non self or the idea that
it's self are inadequate so what we
think of as self is self other than self
division right they talk about a
foundational oneness beyond division it
would be neither of those concepts right
not self nor non self that's different
than the traditional way that is spoken
about in Vedanta which is that at the
foundation of all of it there is
consciousness with a capital C that is
that is different than self right that
can hmm this is basically if you think
about it almost in terms of a unified
field of physics as a field of
potentiality for dynamics to occur in
quantum foam to emerge from etc that
there is reference happening but it's
referenced within the only thing there
is other self reference and that the
foundation of what we think of as self
referentiality happens at the level of
Unified Field interesting now I'm not
saying this is what I think but this is
some of the kind of interpretations
there I will say there are real problems
with most of the models of physicalism
there are real problems with these
models and this is why these are
unsolved famous problems in philosophy
and you even see like you'll see a
couple physical lists like the classic
debate that Sam Harris and Dan Dennett
had under Sam wrote has become free will
was that Dan fundamentally said
consciousness isn't real maybe is a
radical limit Avista it's an illusion
but freewill is real and Sam said
consciousness is fundamentally real an
emergent property of brain but freewill
is available
is a core disagreement on the most
foundational concepts of existentialism
of what actually is both being
physicalists and having the same kind of
critical thinking background agreeing on
a lot of other things so it's part of
why these have been so hard as they're
beyond our current tools of knowing my
pistol my logic tools when we do science
we are studying third-person things
that's very sure do so when we try and
study consciousness which is
first-person by looking at the
third-person core correlates we're
actually doing a category mistake mmm by
assuming that they're the same thing
also when we assume causation when we
get to the level of things that are for
sure via Bell's Theorem a causal our
intuitions get off right and so these
are fascinating and tricky areas what we
can say at the level of what's probably
useful for people right now is that we
can do things with our own subjective
experience of self so what we focus on
we put our attention and the meaning we
give to things that has a real effect on
brain and physiology and we can do
things to our physiology that are not
obviously utilizing our subjectivity
that will affect our subjectivity and
there can be recursive effects between
subjective and objective that can either
depending upon how you do them have the
potential of being virtuous cycles in
more adaptive evolutionary directions or
vicious cycles and so learning how to
use both the conscious direction of our
thought awareness attention and what we
do with our physiology in mutually
reinforcing adaptive ways is I think
what we're interested in wow it's quite
heady stuff no pun intended till you
taste like a philosophy a guy he read
you have a philosophy background yeah
yeah tell us about that what is your
when he's returning been there uh so I
was home-schooled growing out okay and
all the sciences and all the philosophic
traditions were what I was fascinated by
and so a particular home school didn't
have curriculum so I just got to study
what I wanted to know was
interdisciplinary science system science
and the various philosophic traditions
because the the impulse to study science
was impulse to
understand the nature of reality we live
in sure better yeah which is a
philosophic impulse right science is a
method of knowing that correlates to a
particular philosophic system right
philosophical system usually a logical
positivism or the idea that reality
exists objectively objective stuff is
real we can measure it get the same
results so science is a subset of
philosophy it's a particularly useful
meaningful one it doesn't happen to be
an exhaustive one of all sure assurance
yeah yeah and so fortunately got to
study many different Eastern traditions
and Western traditions and my early and
then you know deeply in my kind of
method of understanding any new
discipline is I like to start by going
to the edge of what the hard problems
that are not understood and you know
believe may be unsolvable and then
understand the range of opinions on that
and why and then go back and understand
the core axioms of the field in light of
recognizing where they might actually
have limits
Oh injury all right so let's so with
that perspective with this lens into you
what are the hard problems you bump up
against and enjoy bumping up against in
the biohacker neuro hacker world what
are the what are the growth edges I mean
I I see people acquiring tools and
technologies and ways of modifying their
physiology and their minds constantly
and I provide some of those tools a lot
of the time we're operating a space we
really don't fully understand you know
what we're doing it's this summer
between art and science and I'm sure
half the things that biohackers do are
completely irrelevant and a certain
percentage is probably working counter
to what they actually want to do what do
you find the hard problems are in neuro
hacking or by hacking so neuro hacking
bio hacking and what the hard problems
are in medicine and we kind of looking
at that as medicine moving from
dysfunction to function how can bio
hacking generally thinking of it is
trying to enhance function build on
previous baseline we think of that as
one gradient some of the hard problems
that are not like philosophically hard
problems and
of maybe unsolvable ax T or n stemming
limits but like the Holy Grails of the
space yeah one of them has to do with
complexity okay and so when we're trying
to look at what's going on for an
individual person say we're trying to
look at addressing anxiety for someone
is their anxiety primarily physio genic
or psychogenic and what causes in each
of those if we just look at physio genic
physiologic causes we see a whole good
body of work on the ability for
microbial imbalances in the gut to cause
anxiety anxiety predispositions because
of decreasing the total amount of gaba
produced in the gut or serotonin
producer in the gut or inflammation on
the enteric nervous system or whatever
so if someone went traveling the third
world got a parasite microbiome got off
has never restabilized afterwards know
that could be a tier one cause of
anxiety that no amount of no tropics or
CBT or DBT assures yeah yeah or if they
had minor head trauma where the cat scan
or the MRI didn't show anything but
maybe a qejy would or maybe a SPECT scan
which is this
you know functional fire hydrant sure
went off how we're going to address that
that might require neurofeedback that
might require neurogenic chemistry right
that's going to be totally different
again if they were exposed to mold or
other forms of cytotoxic sure that can
cause anxiety it so there can be genetic
predispositions there and then you can
we can continue to populate there can be
methylation disorders right there surely
thousands of different things and then
the confluence of those things right and
then if we're looking at the psychogenic
side event we're saying someone who had
anxiety since childhood because of kind
of attachment early childhood attachment
stuff of parents versus only after a
very acute trauma even if dealing
crowder are sure they're they're
different psychologically they're
different neurologically and there are
different best practices and therapies
to address all these things and for one
particular person's anxiety we might be
looking at
some confluence of some number of these
factors right where there was a causal
cascade and then that person with
anxiety maybe also has a sleep issue or
not or maybe also has some autoimmunity
or so as we're trying to help them are
we how do we factor all yeah certainly
complexity and personalization yeah is
this possible I mean I I work with
brains every day and I am humbled every
day by how little I actually understand
and my strategy for dealing with that is
you know maslow to a man with a hammer
every problems a nail my hammer is
neurofeedback in meditation and to some
extent nootropics but I view the brain
as a regulatory machine and when I do a
QE G and see something off and it
matches symptoms it's you know it's a
little bit more skill than being a
mechanic perhaps but it's that that
approached it to be let me go region
twins wake this and see what happens I
would I mean I'm working on integrating
lots of different information systems so
that I can you know do visualization do
big data do a better sense of what's
happening but even that will have a
fraction of the type of the degree of
things you're talking about right is it
a solvable problem can we actually bring
in personalized medicine if you will
personalized psychology track data this
way I mean is this being done can we do
it I think we're getting enough
information about the the individual
data points you can do a methylation
analysis you can do a theta beta ratio
you can do you know a blood flow imaging
or something but these measurement tools
are limited by the tool space that they
are using and qejy gives me one thing
because me less than half the EEG only
the dipoles that are at right angles to
the skull and it's a 10,000 foot
population average of average deg across
several minutes so you're missing states
completely only emphasizing traits and
the this you know 30 or 40 big features
in the Q EEG that I look at and then I
operate on in terms of intervening but
it's I default back to that because I
can't do everything because I can't hold
everything in my mind and I can't ask
everyone all the right questions to
tease out what might be going on because
I just
don't understand the brain fully I mean
as you say probably none of us do are we
getting to the place where we're going
to be able to aggregate and analyze and
extract meaning from this complexity or
is the complexity because I've secured
our ability to know what's real I know
it's important yeah I do believe we are
starting in the next few years okay
having an exponential curve this is a
Kurtz wily and predicting here sorts out
in a different direction than rank much
of what we hear about what is going to
happen with brains from singularity okay
as you said we can't hold it you can't
hold it on your brain
okay total amount of information exceeds
our conscious processing by a lot mm-hmm
because of working memory limits mostly
right yeah there's a storage limit the
brain as far as we can tell but there is
a working memory limit for your ability
to consciously you know try to make
sense of not just how many different
metrics but the relationships between
those mixture or ideal material
relationships so say we start looking at
the genome most things aren't affected
by by snips right by one snip there's
very few things that are mostly we're
looking at dynamics combinatorial
dynamics across tens or hundreds of
thousands three effects essentially
right and but that's that's a lot when
you look at you know three billion base
pairs yeah and then we have to deal with
the fact that that doesn't tell us which
ones are actually coding right we have
to look at the epigenome for that which
is not something we do well right now so
we have to look at the transcriptome or
eggs Omega proteome which is all stuff
that is emerging but hard and that's
just the human genes which is not
actually the majority of the genes we
carry around or actually art ours are
human right so so if you think about it
this way right when you're saying the
brain is regulatory system it's a
top-down regulatory says right the
bottom-up regulatory system is the code
layer the genomics the microbiome except
I romics right they are creating a
distributed bottom-up regulation of
individual cell function right and
routine code is sure sure that bottom-up
regulatory capacity is what led to the
the evolutionist top-down regulatory
capacities that get to control larger
groups of cells and tissues working
together in coordination the feedback
relationships between the bottom up and
the top down regulatory systems and all
the dynamics in between is where we're
what I think we're starting to do is map
the human as a cybernetic organism okay
right as a regulatory organism Plex
adaptive system science and kind of
systems modeling to understanding that
better and it is what in computer
science is called a np-complete issue
it's an uncomputable issue okay there's
an uncomputable amount of information
yeah we're not just going to brute force
big data and machine learning and figure
it all out well to chaotic system we
have we do not have infinite precision
therefore any model that steps into time
far at all diverges from the chaotic
system and so yes chaotic meaning
there's some fundamental
unpredictability there our measurement
limits and then there's there is
uncomputable complexity and so what that
means is rather than just depend on
brute force computation we have to
understand the dynamics of causation and
a complex system better so we can
compute the things that actually seem
like they would make sense to happen
right that's the modeling part I think
the modeling part is key and that's it
neuro hoc are what we're really focused
on is taking models like cybernetics
right like complex adaptive systems and
like information theory and putting what
we understand from human biology and
medicine into those more complex models
to understand dynamics better right
complex dynamics and getting to the
place where we can start to aggregate
tremendous amounts of data there and
that of it is has progressively better
sensitivity and specificity and then be
able to process that data where you know
right now for the most part when we look
at a biometric we look at someone's
hemoglobin or their vitamin D or
whatever we're looking at in
relationship to a reference range sure
but when we look at someone's someone
has a kind of dynamic homeostasis right
I actually really like it we're at homeo
dynamics it's a better word because the
stasis is nonsense as you mentioned
sorry
I need your response right here the word
homeostasis sure life is not stasis we
have these homeo dynamic yeah and then
thriving health has to do with the homeo
dynamic capacity and resilience across
all of those homeo dynamic axes right
mm-hmm aging is decreased homeo dynamic
capacity across some of the axes does
that mean decreased range of variability
in actually decreased capacity to have a
stressor right some things that's trying
to create deviation from homeostasis and
the ability to stay within the homeo
dynamic range so then if which means
less resilience so to be concrete things
like insulin or cortisol rotla to
insulin rises when you consume sugar
right when you know it's a signaling
molecule cells suck up the glucose
insulin goes back down to chronically
pretty sure the insulin system to the
top of its range eventually it stops
varying and we call that type 2 diabetes
and on the way there the kind of
syndrome X dynamics where fasting
insulin levels raise you get insulin
resistance at the level cells now you
take sugar and in your blood sugar is
going to go further out of balance no
longer
causing more effect on other systems are
affected by blood sugar so more than
pathophysiology so we're defining here
aging is not disease because disease
we'd actually say is the deviation from
homeostatic range or homeo dynamic range
where some metric actually goes out of
effective range and then you get a
pathophysiologic cascade okay
so aging is not that it's the increased
susceptibility for that so it's
increased susceptibility for disease
because someone could have all of their
markers within homeostatic state range
mm-hmm but more sensitive to them being
able to go out of range from whatever
stresses so they're less label to sit in
the in the in the healthy basin of the
phase space so to speak right okay sorry
and so what we're interested in here is
how do we where someone already has
disease dynamics going on how do we
identify specifically what caused
deviation from homeostasis on which
dynamics
what was the causal cascade that
happened and how do we specifically
reverse it like we mentioned with the
anxiety are we are we keel ating
neurotoxins or are we fixing the gut
brain access or those are very different
things that require specific addressing
of what the causal cascade was so this
is not let's say going to insulin the
insulin insensitivity that cells
experience after high levels of insulin
that's not the disease itself that is
the failure of the dynamic range correct
and we call these diseases things like
diabetes and Alzheimer's or other things
because of the failure now there are
some people who get type 2 diabetes who
did not consume too much carbohydrates
relative to what they burn but they are
deficient in chromium or vanadium that
are nary to actually have insulin
process that receptors so there are
other dynamics that can go on which is
why we actually have to understand what
are what is the entire causal phase
space of what can cause an imbalance all
the things that could be involved and
this is what we've sucked at at medicine
so far is dealing with complex causation
yeah feud causation straightforward
right so injury pretty straightforward
and so we're going to be able to address
that in a clearer way but where the
causation is either delayed in time
right so something happened and it led
to a slow deviation from homeo dynamics
over the course of years or decades it's
hard to assess what it was yeah
or where it's multifactorial there's
many different things going on and where
it's a combination of some
multifactorial set that's different for
different people so I don't think ms is
a disease I think it is and I don't
think Alzheimer's is a disease or
anxiety I think they are conditions
where some cluster of symptoms and
biomarkers come together what we call
with that but the actual causal etiology
going into it can be radically different
from one person to the next so Laurie
syndrome less of a disease a cluster of
symptoms that may have multiple causal
features interesting I saw a study out
of UCLA a couple weeks ago that suggests
Alzheimer's insulin insensitivity if you
will can be reduced simply through
behavioral mechanism to a bunch of
people off of all the meds off of
anything instead of doing
specific intervention they said let's do
lifestyle things and did you know paleo
diets and exercise and lo and behold
symptomatic Alzheimer's individuals
showed recovery of some function this is
fairly magical things there was a study
out a couple weeks ago showing that even
in people with type 2 and type 1
diabetes who have no beta islet cells
essentially anymore in their pancreas
producing insulin short period of
fasting if it was 12 or 24 hours a very
short period seems to cause a read if ur
enchi a ssin of non beta islet cells
into beta islet cells to produce insulin
right that flies in the face of what we
thought of in the disease model diabetes
where it's either autoimmune or it's
toxic from the sugar essentially that
kills in some person cells once they go
on to gone that does not appear to be
accurate is this the kind of thing that
your your listing is the main thing that
the idea that we don't produce new
neurons right that was an old idea
driven we realized you know Genesis
happens and it can be up regulated yeah
and that it was only in three places and
now it's pretty much everywhere you look
in the brain we're finding new actually
button stem cells so and so can we
increase pluripotent stem cell
production and their differentiation
throughout the connectome and can we
increase neural protection and
synaptogenesis and yeah like we're
learning a lot about how that works
any when you have a system that
generated itself it's a self generating
system the idea that it just could not
generate those tissues that it
originally generated again doesn't make
that much sense obviously capacity to do
it and then the capacity decreases or
turns off for some reasons those then
likely are modulated to turn on again so
sure when we think about life extension
how do we increase progenitor stem cells
hmm how do we increase the rate of
purging senescence structures how do we
protect cells from senescence these are
all things that happen already sure they
can start happening in at suboptimal
levels for a lot of reasons we can
support them happening in optimal levels
and maybe even beyond previous genetic
optimality right just to give us
discrete example the gerontologist teach
courses in aging is a term
aging called antagonistic pleiotropy the
idea that a mechanism that is healthy at
one point in life is harmful another
point in life and the telomeres you know
the shortening end caps that prevent
replication forever when you're young
prevents cancer from running away with
yourselves when you're old keeps
fibroblasts in your collagen from
cleaning themselves up and they become
homes for a pro cancer environment
basically so this kind of thing we're
identifying where the natural arc of
development may not be optimal for long
term performance and turning these
things back on and controlling it I mean
from point of view telomeres you know
for a long time that was of course the
Holy Grail in antisemitism years you
know ridiculously it would probably just
cause huge amounts of cancer so we can't
simply reach in and turn one thing on I
mean this is something I struggle with a
neurofeedback it's not reaching in and
dialing up and down different
neurotransmitters or different you know
brainwave ratios when I perturb a system
the system reorganizes and I'm never
quite sure how it's going to reorganize
this is uh you know little frustrating
sometimes so if we think of it as
increasing system resilience right
homeodomain capacity because it is a
self-organizing system and the
complexity is well beyond what we're
going to understand in a momentary view
right we're never going to factor all of
the dynamics happening probably even in
one cell but we can understand the
dynamics that are involved in its some
of the key ones in its own regulatory
dynamics and how we can increase its
regulatory capacity and so in general do
we see things like redox signaling
decreasing inefficiency in cells yes
yeah so this is why all the nicotinamide
right aside stuff has been so if you can
up regulate the NAD+ NADH ratio there's
a lot of cool things that happen yeah do
we see a CP decreasing inside of cells
yes do all the things that cells do need
those chemicals sure yeah if we can
support mitochondrial biogenesis if we
can support ATP production efficiency
and krebs cycle upregulation yep if we
support protection of the mitochondria
so they don't become senescent right
these are key things that what exactly
is that going to do what is going to
help the complex dynamics of everything
the cells are doing happened better and
so I think those are one of the key
things we so you know we were saying
earlier there are specific sources of
pathology right causes of deviation from
homeostasis that we want to identify
specifically in Reverse you have the
Jin's toxins deficiencies etc then there
are general system dynamics that support
system resilience and we want to support
those even though the effects of that
are going to be general increase
well-being in crossing systems so EEG
regulation is going to produce you know
how much is it going to affect a
particular gastrointestinal dynamic well
it depends on what all the causal
dynamic oh yeah it should move it in the
right direction to the degree that it's
creating better sympathetic
parasympathetic you know ratio dynamics
etc yeah so we want to in general
support the homeostatic processes that
are fundamental and get better at
diagnosing individual sources of
pathology and reversing them this is
great I mean this actually ties into how
I often frame there a feedback for
people and they say oh how to do this
and I'll say well we're probably going
to give you more resources and all the
regulatory domains of sleep stress and
attention and what that means is
resilience right and we can probably
reach in and do more specific things for
you but let's see what happens first
when we bring the resilience way up and
get you sleeping like a rocket will and
being creative and flexible let's do
that for the first few weeks and then we
can go in and try to target the thing
you think you care about me and usually
the thing that they really want to work
on sorts itself out along the way
towards just building everything that
the complexity of the interconnectedness
of everything is again why specialties
have failed at complex illnesses yeah
but it's also so fascinating because you
know we can look at a structural issue
right like a postural issue or
osteoarthritis that's causing can
continues inflammation within the
inflammatory molecules right cytokines
can cross the blood-brain barrier cause
neural inflammation and damage to neural
circuits yeah
also where the continuous pain dynamic
is causing sympathetic feedback into the
brain which then is going to cause
effects on all the things the brain is
regulating for helps on perspective life
and what needed fixed was a structural
issue in a knee right right and or mold
in the environment or a runaway process
of dysfunctional information processing
in the brain from a particular
psychologic meaning making pattern right
so can can structural issues and joints
or psychological patterns of focus and
meaning making or things going on in the
gut or affect any other system in the
body yes this is what's fascinating is
why trying to separate neurology and
gastroenterology and oncology has a pile
here yeah and so now it's how do we
synthesize what we understand about the
parts to understand what happens for
whole systems and what happens across
systems so now you're doing this at the
Niraj collective this idea of bringing
in different aggregate data types and
modeling and trying to figure out what
is the meaningful inflection points for
these models where you know what wears
change happening that's very you know
high level and and those are the kind of
projects that frustrate PhD students for
you know 20 30 years yeah I think it's
great I'm you know I'm incredibly noble
pursuit to enter those big questions I
also know you guys are doing something's
a little bit more okay here are some
things we can actually do this a product
you've produced called qualia which is
Ana tropics is that is it an entropic
space okay do you consider it in tropic
or is it more than that is that a good
frame for it is that too limiting I
think that's a fine frame as you know
the term no tropic is a little bit
loosely defined in terms of how its
generous yeah how do you define it
well I would I would in general start by
making the distinctions between brain
nutrient no tropic and smart drug which
are apparently used kind of in relation
to each other yeah it's worth
distinguishing so brain nutrient means
something that you'd normally get from a
dietary source that's critical to some
part of neurologic function that can
often be a suboptimal levels precursors
like tyrosine all your amino acids fatty
acids vitamins minerals that are part of
neural dynamics and
when we talk about medical deficiency
we're talking about a level at which
acute pathologies happening below that
level there's a pretty huge range
between medical deficiency and
optimality hmm right and so we can call
that subclinical deficiency or sub
optimality and so there's heaps of brain
nutrients that depending upon what kind
of tests we do we see in suboptimal
levels all the time right okay vitamin D
is a puck sure yeah
even in Southern California even in
Southern California and and because it's
not at a level four you know rickets
right someone has a you know thirty
vitamin D traditional medical process
hasn't addressed that but when we you
know have deeper insight about where
optimality occurs it's a far away way
which is why the vitamin D
supplementation is meaningful same would
be true with omega-3 or tyrosine or Nick
cetera so brain nutrients that are
either hard to source adequately in diet
or where modern lifestyle has used them
faster so if we're talking about Heidi
or stress lives where B vitamins are in
a process faster or whatever those are
meaningful or you're a vegan if you are
eating anything with s B vitamins in it
so tight you know any kind of dietary
limitation yeah things to address
nootropics starting with you know
defining piracetam as that field is some
chemical that can increase some aspect
of cognitive function beyond baseline
without meaningfully negative side
effects thank you for including that
last piece the original definition
essentially I this is one of the axes I
love to grind you know I'm all over the
new trophic forms and things and I can't
tell you the number of times I have to
resist reaching through the computer and
throttling some kid who thinks that
modafinil is mini trophic yeah nothing
with our people with a significant side
effect should be considered and I'm
guessing you have the same perspective I
do if your performance is already
relatively good why would you risk side
effects for small incremental
improvements Supra baseline improvements
you're trying to remedy a deficit that
okay maybe you need to risk some things
to get a problem sorted out but I don't
understand the incredible marketing and
consumer push to seek for you
all of these drugs and compounds that
have someone have very very significant
side effects on the off chance that
they're going to be you know designed
for your sort of your chemistry and give
you that little boost I don't understand
the the philosophy feel behind that this
idea that you can you can reach for
something that might not be unilaterally
good just in case it might you know
that's that seems very um non nootropic
you know to me so to speak so the topic
of risk benefit ratio yeah is core to
Western medicine right and it's partly
why we only have a disease model and we
don't have an optimization model is
because in the disease model there is a
risk to not treating the thing right
pain problem so some risk of a treatment
seems warranted sure and you have to
make sure that the risk makes sense to
possible benefit if people are already
generally healthy and this also why
longevity research hasn't you know had a
lot of support until recently or any
kind of optimization which provides been
left to biohackers is how much risk can
we justify for how much benefit beyond
baseline right
it's actually a really deep question and
it's a question that should be answered
individually within a range that is
reasonable for the field as a whole to
pursue now I think bodybuilding and
steroids is a classic example of this
okay so can people perform in
fundamentally increased ways with
anabolic steroids that they couldn't
otherwise obviously right you know
otherwise you wouldn't ban them in
sports is it and you know were the
people who are really pioneering this
risking their health and if many of them
experienced the downsides of that
already totally yeah and for them at
least knowing that quite clearly for
many of them it was worth it because
that's what they want to do right like
the same reason anyone would do anything
that was not a smart longevity decision
for what the passages where and then the
field of steroids itself evolved from a
lot of that experimentation to where the
you know that some of the Psalms today
have
compared to the early anabolics have
radically more benefit for much less
risk yep
partly evolved by kind of the citizen
science happening in that space that
just for ethical reasons couldn't happen
in formal ressure sure so it's a very
interesting topic right it is a place
where citizen science is always going to
be advancing the front edge and I would
say all of the Psychonauts working with
deep psychedelics are in the same place
and so one of the things we really like
is for people who are for whatever
reason inclined to do their own research
give them better quantified self tools
and learn from that if it's outside of
what we can do formal research on and
then you know be able to take the formal
research from the crowdsource to get a
very big level essentially that's great
now with regard to what the appropriate
risk benefit dynamics are yeah so you
mentioned modafinil and take it further
methamphetamine definitely increases
certain cognitive capacities and it
kills the flu virus it has a number of
positive medical credentials yeah and it
has very real side effects and so if
someone is in a combat situation and
then you have stay awake a little bit
longer
they have meth might make sense right
part of how those drugs were developed
yeah for general use for your midterms
you know it's not a good idea now if we
look at how much off-label adderall and
modafinil and redbull and whatever right
you know happens for those purposes this
was one of the main reasons we decided
to make quality was not only are the
down regulation and side effects pretty
significant of most of those but even
the positives are fairly narrow mm-hmm
right so if you have if you use it a
presynaptic dopamine agonist right like
adderall you will get increased focus
but you might actually get
simultaneously decreased working memory
we would have seen on that is clear
which is not the kind of total
intelligence that we're interested in it
as well as you know anxiety irritability
depersonalization all those other
dynamics and then of course because it's
an external override of an internal
regulatory system yeah
regulation independence you know and so
what we're really interested in I'm what
I'm sure you've been interested in the
in the space was can we understanding
this system more completely and nowhere
near total completely but more
completely right we're not just trying
to a single molecule intervention can we
have a much more comprehensive set of
positive effects rather than a narrow
set without the negative effects in real
time and without down regulation so that
when someone gets off of them they're
not experiencing addiction come down but
if anything experiencing long-term
upregulation of the capacity of their
system so that's obviously that's the
design principle with which we approach
the whole space quality and all the
products and development so follows your
first product then yeah what's in it I
haven't dug into the ingredients at this
point so brain nutrients and no tropics
okay and so as you know when people
start in the no tropic space usually
they dive into a seagull calling for
sure
shirring and so rasa Tam's and some
choline donors that are like the the
foundation for memory augmentation
sensory nerve motor nerve you know
acuity etc so but which rasa thames you
use are going to have a bunch of other
differential effects and rasa taking
impress them are very different
creatures oh yeah and also are we going
to address the ability for the
acetylcholine once it's produced to get
across the synapse are we looking at
acetylcholinesterase inhibitors are we
making sure that the acetyl groups
aren't rate limiting for the choline
that's there that people aren't getting
over cholinergic we look in different
choline donors central phenoxy is going
to act on the central nervous system
more than alpha GPC on the peripheral
nervous system if we look at the
conversion of uridine to Citi choline to
phosphatidylcholine LDPC to
acetylcholine you're also going to get
different peak plasma times when HMS
Eagle : kicks in so if you want to be
able to have less of a spike and more of
a continuous process you might put a
number of those so we focused on like
with acetylcholine we're looking at what
is the whole acetylcholine regulatory
process so and how can we address any of
the rate limiting factors and make sure
that
we're we're acting on peripheral nerves
were reacting on central nervous system
differentially more is what we want to
be doing it the kind of pharmacodynamics
and kinetics of so not just where it's
acting but how long it's operating for
and those curves are things that would
really look at how much acetylcholine
we're producing it so that you've also
got not just a siedel donors which is
why people love alkar right seal
quarantine and one of the reasons and
today I know what protein doesn't kreb
cycle is b5 is often a rate limiting
factor for the synthesis rather the
acetylation of choline so you know what
are the right ratios of those things
together and then how much acetylcholine
support for how much NMDA upregulation
and then where do you get rate limiting
effects in terms of the total cellular
energy to process more acetylcholine and
then all of that just acetylcholine yeah
then we look at glutamate and typically
it's pretty common that rasa terms of am
packing light properties yeah certainly
uh any rs.10 does and you kept which
reviews know I always get confused new
pep seems to have race at am like
properties could not be a race at am
correct I mean I look at the structure
and doesn't have a protein ring that's
correct so it called racetam like and am
packing like okay as of up regulating
acetylcholine uptake in the NMDA complex
and up regulating glutamate uptake at
the AMPA complex but it is actually not
structurally either of them okay but
it's very interesting it's a precursor
to cyclopropyl glycine it is neuro
protective it's anti excited is anti
excitotoxins the way that it brings
excessive glutamate outside of the
synapse so it's a very interesting
molecule a new pepsin quality as well
great now there are plenty of things
that we would have in qualia if there
was different regulatory dynamics okay
but you know so we're working within
both the general well-tolerated space
the effective space the and the legal
space sure yeah people micro dosing LSD
or psilocybin has a lot of neat effects
we can
that's that arising right um not yet not
yet so actually that's face of the
appropriate legal categorization of
medicines as its base that we have
worked in and intend to more because
it's important so more political legal
and regulatory not at the physiology but
at the body politic exactly interesting
so when you look at say two men offend
being over-the-counter hmm as a legacy
thing in the toxicity of it came to hair
to pot having been illegal for and still
illegal and so many plays for so long
it's just nonsense right right and we
can look at the whole history of why
those nonsense decisions were made but
they're not just nonsense they're really
bad for people
yeah because pot doesn't cause liver
damage and acetaminophen does and it but
it addresses the same pain dynamics of
people using it man
yeah but you can put a few minutes on it
with opiates and that prevents people
from taking all the opiates and
overdosing in theory that's that's of
course the title three vicodin kind of
approach is to combine to seem innocent
to avoid to to say hey it's going to
kill you if you take too much don't take
too much and so then people take too
much and get liver damage right right so
it's not a good idea but maybe they
didn't that wasn't well thought out
right so um it's been heady stuff Daniel
thank you so much for sharing a video
wisdom where can people find out more
about you other projects do you have
going on how can they dig into the the
the Daniel list that that we have here
in front of us a little more if they
have had their interest sparked as far
as the topics were talking about here
neural high kinetics neural hacker calm
okay a good place to go check it out
great publishing more information there
and I want to say that the work that you
are doing and neurofeedback and the fact
that you're scaling it with quality
control and with the systems that allow
that to happen that's one of the areas
that if you hadn't done it we would have
eventually got into because it's
critical and we think it is one of the
really most meaningful neuro hacks that
has the least the least damage box
really small downside is if done well
right yeah yeah it's real super high
reward possibility so I'm excited too
look at if there's a way we can partner
and support what you're doing I'm sure
there is we're both in Southern
California so we should very at least
try to work that great so can they fall
can folks while you on Twitter Instagram
LinkedIn what's the what's if there's
one of you know follow you and here so
you drop wisdom and see all the things
you do what's the best way to do that
Facebook is probably best Facebook all
right great
so today's guest has been Daniel
spectrum Berger of the neuro hacker
collective we packed more into this hour
than I think most shows we've had I'm
going to go back and listen to myself
and look up a few terms which is great
so I rarely have to stretch myself that
way I really appreciate it
so folks it has been another show of
head first doctor he'll take care of
your brains and we'll see you next week
[Music]